Guide to the Civil Service Merit Council Records WAG.114
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Civil Service Merit Council Records
1970s-2000s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Civil Service Merit Council
Gorsky, Sheila
WAG.114
12 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
Scope and Contents
The records consist of organizational reports and correspondence, notices and flyers, publicity materials and background files on such topics as legislation, the merit system, payroll issues, school construction, job titles and whistle-blowers.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Civil Service Merit Council was founded in 1971 by Alfred Engel (d. 2007), an engineer who had worked in many New York City agencies and was active as a chapter chairman in the Civil Service Technical Guild, Local 375 (AFSCME, DC 37), and attorney Julian Jackson. Engel became the council's first president. The purpose of the Merit Council was to advocate for strict adherence to civil service examination results, and against patronage, favoritism, outsourcing and other abuses in civil service employment. It is a non-partisan coalition of individuals and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Civil Service Merit Council, 1995. The accession number associated with this gift is 2000.005.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Municipal officials and employees |z New York (State) |z New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Government employee unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Civil service -- New York (State) -- New York.; Civil Service Merit Council; Gorsky, Sheila; Engel, Alfred, d. 2007; Civil Service Merit Council
- Membership; Bank Papers; Correspondence; Meeting Notices; Favoritism; Hearings, 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
- Dinners; Events; Meetings; Correspondence; Reports; Lobbying, Late 1970s-1990s (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings; Articles; Charter; Personnel Policy; Watchdog, 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
- Membership; Civil Service Technical Guild; Dues Letters; Watchdog 1994-1996, 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 4)
- Watchdog; Board of Examiners; 1978 Capital Cash Flow; 1972 City Council Report-Assault on the Merit System; Civil Service Legislation; Corruption; Various Court Cases, 1970s- 1990s (Box 5)
- Watchdog 1978, 1984, 1986, 1987; Publicity; News Releases; Newspaper Articles; Letters to the Editor; Awards; Dues 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1970s-1990s (Box 6)
- Organizational Chart; Flyers; Newspaper Clippings, Articles; Pictures; Statement of Edward Koch before the NYS Commission on Government Integrity 4/5/89; NYC Affirmative Employment Plan 1991, 1980s-1990s (Box 7)
- Subject Files I-O Including: Legislation; Managerial; Mayor20s Office; Merit System, undated (Box 8)
- Subject Files P-S Including: Payroll Probe; Personnel Files; Provisionals; State Retirement; School Construction, undated (Box 9)
- Subject Files S-W Including: The Superintendent Hearing; Teachers; Titles; Whistle Blowers, undated (Box 10)
- CSMC Dinner 05, 06, 2005-2006 (Box 11)
- Union Invitations to CSMC 2006 Dinner (2 Folders) (Box 11)
- Civil Service Merit Council Misc. Papers, undated (Box 11)
- Legal Actions (2 Folders), undated (Box 11)
- CSMC Case Files- Fitzgerald v. Rosenzwig, undated (Box 11)
- CSMC Letters, undated (Box 11)
- Merit Council Mailings 2002 (Box 11)
- CSMC Membership Material 2002 (Box 11)
- News Articles, ect., undated (Box 11)
- Civil Service Merit Council-25th Anniversary Dinner, undated (Box 11)
- Additional Information on 25th Anniversary, undated (Box 11)
- Board Meeting Minutes Jan. 2000, 2001, 1999, 1999-2001 (Box 11)
- General Meeting Membership Minutes-Various Years(Binder), undated (Box 11)
- CSMC Elections 1999 (Box 12)
- CSMC Elections 1998 (Box 12)
- CSMC Official Seal 1988, 1998 (Box 12)
- Merit Council Board Meeting 2000 (Box 12)
- CSMC Elections 2000 (Box 12)
- Correspondence 1998 (Box 12)
- Correspondence 1999 (Box 12)
- Correspondence 2000-2001 (Box 12)
- Management Council Board Meeting 2001 (Box 12)
- Mathew Farrell-Candidate for City Council-26th District, undated (Box 12)
- Bank Statement 2001 (Box 12)
- Resumes Honorees 2004 (Box 12)
- CSMC Meetings and Minutes 2004 (Box 12)
- CSMC Correspondence 2003 (Box 12)
- CSMC Dinner Nov. 2003 (Box 12)
- CSMC Meetings 2005 (Box 12)
- Resumes CSMC 2005-2006 (Box 12)
- CSMC Meeting Notices 2003 (Box 12)
- CSMC Membership 2003 (Box 12)
- CSMC Minutes 2000-2003 (Box 12)
- CSMC Misc. Material 1999-2000 (Box 12)
- CSMC Membership 2004-2005 (Box 12)
- CSMC Letters for Unions and Draft Editorial Piece in The Chief 2003 (Box 12)
- CSMC Dinner Oct 17, 2002 (Box 12)
- Elections 2002 (Box 12)
- CSMC Dinner 2004 (Box 12)
- CSMC Election 2005 (Box 12)
- CSMC Election 2003, 2004 (Box 12)
- CSMC Legal Case 2003 (Box 12)
- Archived Website, Feb 6, 2009-Mar 6, 2009
  Scope and Content Note
  The Civil Service Merit Council, founded in 1971, is a non-partisan coalition of individuals and organizations whose primary purpose was to increase the level of efficiency and integrity of government. The Merit Council's primary objective is to ensure that all appointments to the New York civil service shall be made through competitive examinations to properly classified positions from among persons duly qualified without regard to race, religion, age, sex, or political opinion or affiliation. The Council is dedicated to preserving and advancing the rights and tenure of all persons in the Merit System.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.